Guide to the Great Britain, Parliament, 1628, Journal of the Proceedings
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
[Journal of the proceedings in Parliament]
1627-03-17-1628-06-26
OSBORN FB165
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.23
(1 volume)
Anonymous 17th century MS. Includes speeches, petitions, messages, and committee proceedings. Most printed in Rushworth, v.i., but the versions in this MS are much longer and more complete. Includes the Commons' remonstrance to the King, April 1626. Signature of Thomas Cole on inside cover and his stamp. From the library of Dr Cox Macro and later of Hudson Gurney. The historical MSS Commission reported on this MS in the XII Report, Part IX, p.123, #XIV.
Great Britain. Parliament (1628)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a complete inventory of the contents of Osborn fb165. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
- Osborn fb165
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - "A Commission to the Lordes and others of the privie Counsell concerning the present raising of Money" (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      [1627/8 Feb 29]
      3 p.
      MS copy. Rushworth, v.i, 614.
      p.1-3.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - "A privie seale for the transporting of horses and armes" (Box 1)
      [1627/8 Jan 30]
      1 p.
      MS copy. Rushworth, v.i, 612.
      p.4.
  - ELIOT, SIR JOHN, 1592-1632
    - [Petition to the King, 1627], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      4 p.
      MS copy. Presents arguments against
      the legality of the forced loan
      which he has refused to pay.
      Rushworth, v.i, 429.
      p.11-14.
  - COTTON, SIR ROBERT, 1571-1631
    - "Sir Robert Cotton's speech before the Lordes of the Councell, advising for a parliament, and discoursing of the dangers wherein the Kingdom now stands" (Box 1)
      [1627/8 Jan 29]
      10 p.
      MS copy. Rushworth, v.i, 467.
      p.15-26.
  - [JESUITS. ENGLAND]
    - "A coppie of a letter found amongst the Jesuits taken lately addressed to the Father and Rector at Bruxels" (Box 1)
      [1627/8 ca. Feb]
      7 p.
      MS copy. Concerns the calling of
      Parliament. Rushworth, v.i, 1628
      (shortened form).
      p.27-33.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [The King's speech at the opening of Parliament, followed by the speech of the Lord Keeper, 1627/7 Mar 17], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      12 p.
      MS copies. Rushworth, v.i, 476 ff.
      p.34-36.
  - FINCH, JOHN FINCH, 1ST BARON, 1584-1660
    - [The speech of the Speaker of the House of Commons at the opening of Parliament and the reply of the Lord Keeper, 1627/8 Mar 19] (Box 1)
      21 p.
      MS copies. Rushworth, v.i, 480-489
      (with variations).
      p.46-66.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1628
    - [Parliament's petition to the King for a general fast, 1627/8 Mar 20], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      2 p.
      MS copy. Rushworth, v.i, 498-499.
      p.67-68.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [The King's propositions to Parliament concerning supply, 1627/8 Mar 26], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      MS copy. Rushworth, v.i, 513.
      p.69.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1628.
    - [The debate on supply, 1627/8 Mar 22], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      14 p.
      MS copy. Speeches by Francis Seymour,
      Baron Seymour (1590?-1664); Sir
      Robert Phelips (1586?-1638); Thomas
      Wentworth, 1st earl of Strafford
      (1593-1641); Sir Benjamin Rudyard
      (1572-1658). Rushworth, v.i, 499 ff.
      p.70-84.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1628.
    - [Resolutions of the House of Commons concerning the liberties of the subject, 1628 Mar 26 - Apr 1], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      MS copy.
      p.85-86.
  - CRESHELD, RICHARD
    - [Speech in Parliament of the liberties of the subject, 1628 Mar 25], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      MS copy. Rushworth, v.i, 506.
      p.87-100
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1628
    - [The petition against recusants, 1628 Mar 28], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      6 p.
      Contemporary MS copy.
      Rushworth, v.i, 516-519.
      p.101-106.
  - COKE, SIR JOHN, 1563-1644
    - [Speech at a conference of both Houses on the petition against recusants, 1628 Mar 28], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Rushworth, v.i, 514.
      p.107-109.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1628.
    - [The debate on the King's propositions for supply, 1628 Apr 2], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      5 p.
      Short speeches by many speakers.
      Rushworth, v.i, 520-523.
      p.110-114.
  - BUCKINGHAM, GEORGE VILLIERS, 1ST DUKE OF, 1592-1628
    - "The duke of Buckingham his speech to his Majesty at the Council_Table, on Friday the 4th of April 1628", [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. On the
      subsidies granted to the King by
      Parliament. Rushworth, v.i, 525.
      p.115-117.
  - COKE, SIR JOHN, 1563-1644
    - "Sir John Coke's relation of his Majesty's acceptance of the subsidies, 4th April 1628", [n.d.] (Box 1)
      MS copy. CJ, I, 879.
      p.118.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - "His Majesty's answer to the Petition presented him by both houses of Parliament concerning matters of religion 10 April 1628", [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Rushworth, v.i, 516.
      p.119-122.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1628.
    - [The conference between the two Houses concerning the liberties of the subject, 1628 Apr 3], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      155 p.
      Contemporary MS copies. Includes
      speeches by Sir Dudley Digges, Edward
      Littleton, baron of Littleton, John
      Seldon, and Sir Edward Coke, and
      the arguments against them by the
      attorney general. Also included are
      copies of the legal precedents used
      as evidence on both sides.
      LJ, III, 717 and Rushworth, v.i, 527.
      p.123-282.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [The King's message to the House of Commons on the necessity of supply, delivered by Secretary Coke, 1628 Apr 11], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Rushworth, v.i, 538.
      p.283-284.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1628.
    - [The presentation to the King against the billeting of soldiers, and a copy of the petition and the King's reply, 1628 Apr 14] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copies.
      Rushworth, v.i, 540.
      p.285-298.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1628.
    - [The proceedings against the Earl of Suffolk, 1628 Apr 14-17], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      MS copy. Suffolk is accused of
      slandering Seldon. CJ, I, 883-884.
      p.299-303.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1628.
    - [Proceedings against Dr Roger Manwaring, 1628 Apr-Jun], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copies. Francis Rous'
      (1579-1659) charge against Manwaring
      (1590-1653); a brief of Manwaring's
      tenets; the censure of Manwaring in
      the Lords and Manwaring's submission.
      Rushworth, v.i, 577, 605.
      p.304-310.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. JUDGES.
    - "The Answer of the judges... upon the case of habeus corpus", [n.d.] (Box 1)
      [1628 Apr 21]
      8 p.
      MS copy. Rushworth, v.i, 509.
      p.311-318.
  - WARWICK, ROBERT RICH, 2ND EARL OF, 1587-1658
    - "The Earl of Warwick's speech in the upper house of parliament on Tuesday the 22nd of April 1628" (Box 1)
      p.319-323.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1628.
    - [Proceedings in Parliament concerning the Petition of Right, 1628 Apr-Jun], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      100 p.
      speeches, debates, and resolutions of
      both Houses; messages and answers of
      the King and a copy of the petition.
      Rushworth, v.i, 1628.
      p.324-428.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1628.
    - [The remonstrance against the George Villiers, 1st duke of Buckingham, 1628 Jun 16], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. Includes a
      calendar of the shipping taken by th
      enemy. Rushworth, v.i, 619.
      p.429-450.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1626.
    - [Remonstrance to the King, 1626 Apr], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Rushworth, v.i, 243.
      p.451-456.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [The King's speech at the opening of Parliament, 1628/9 Jan 24], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Rushworth, v.i, 644.
      p.457-458.
  - ROUS, FRANCIS, 1579-1659
    - [Speech made in Parliament concerning religion, 1628/9 Jan 26] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. Warning
      against Arminianism.
      Rushworth, v.i, 645, and fb 158.
      p.459-464.
  - [USSHER, JAMES, ABP. OF ARMAGH, 1581-1656]
    - [Petition of the Irish bishops against popery, 1626 Nov 26, followed by an account of the petition 1627 Apr 22], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copies. George
      Downham, Bp. of Derry (d.1634). See
      fb 155 page 479 for another copy.
      p.465-468.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [The King's speech at the adjournment of Parliament, 1628 Jun 26], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Rushworth, v.i, 631.
      p.475-476.